Mohammed Uzair Mohiuddin

Email: mohammeduzair07@gmail.com Mobile: +1-945-2162329Badges: YourAcclaim

Website LinkedIn GitHub

Professional Summary

Skilled engineer with over 3.5 years of experience in designing, implementing, and maintaining cloud infrastructure solutions across various platforms. My aim is to design highly scalable and fault-tolerant systems for an esteemed organization, which would be rewarding in terms of learning experience and contribute to organizational and personal growth.

EXPERIENCE

HashiCorp

Lead Support Engineer - Secure Backline

Aug. 2022 - Present

- o Led high-impact customer escalations involving complex technical issues with Vault and Boundary, significantly improving customer retention.
- Played a key role in the initial deployment of the Kubernetes Vault Secrets Operator for a significant customer, leading to organizational-wide adoption.
- o Collaborated closely with engineering teams to reproduce critical bugs before GA and contributed to the improvement of Vault's resilience at scale through supportability requests such as addressing lease explosions.
- o Developed an internal automation tool using Terraform to help junior engineers spin up reproduction environments quickly.
- Set up monitoring for HashiCorp Boundary using Prometheus and Grafana, creating actionable dashboards that enhanced visibility into system performance.
- Participated in the Bring Your Questions initiative, offering deep technical insights into HashiCorp Vault and Boundary to both internal teams and customers.
- o Partnered in authoring "Vault on Kubernetes Deployment Guide", provided multiple training sessions to increase team's efficiency to handle production-grade kubernetes issues.

WALTLabs.io

Cloud Engineer

Apr. 2022 - Aug. 2022

- o Developed and maintained Kubernetes-based infrastructure on both on-prem and AWS environments, managing over 50+ nodes.
- Developed a POC custom automation tool that monitors the health of nodes in a Kubernetes cluster, detecting issues such as high resource usage and node failures.
- Automated infrastructure provisioning and configuration using Terraform, and Ansible reducing manual intervention by 70%.
- Created Helm charts for Kubernetes to automate the deployment of microservices and ensure consistency across environments.
- Tested disaster recovery (DR) plans with AWS Route 53 and Multi-AZ RDS, ensuring near-zero downtime in failover scenarios.

BETSOL

Associate Site Reliability Engineer

Jan. 2021 - Jan. 2022

- Automated the creation of AKS clusters using Terraform Templates.
- o Designed and implemented an Azure Web Application Gateway to perform path-based routing based on the content present in the HTTP request headers.
- Setup Cloudflare DNS zones via Terraform and was actively involved in performing CURD operations for DNS A records, Page rules and SSL certificates.
- Automated the creation of an Azure Compute Image with the help of Packer, Jenkins, and Nexus.
- Created Ansible roles to call web services which configured the Virtual Machines on First Boot.
- Designed and implemented the networking model of the project including partitioning the VNETs into component-based subnets, implementing VNET peering across regions to facilitate communication across the different entities of the solution.
- Worked on Terraform Cloud in order to setup Infra on Azure such as VNETs, Subnets, VMSS, KeyVaults and Created a CI/CD Pipeline for the same via Jenkins.

- Observability as Code DataDog Alerts creation using Terraform to monitor the health of AKS nodes, Container restarts etc
- Was involved in making hot fixes, Provided support in the roll-out and deployment of new application features to facilitate iterative development.

PROJECTS

Vault Integration in Kubernetes

HashiCorp Vault, Kubernetes, Terraform

- Implemented HashiCorp Vault within Kubernetes for secure secrets management and automated secret injection into application pods at runtime.
- Leveraged Vault's capability to generate dynamic secrets for databases (e.g., PostgreSQL) on-the-fly, reducing the risk of credential exposure and ensuring secure database connections.
- Defined and managed various secret engines in Vault, including key/value stores and cloud-based secrets engines such as AWS and Azure.
- Created policies and access controls to limit the exposure of secrets, ensuring that only authorized applications and users could access sensitive data.

Avaya Proactive Outreach Manager - Component of CCaaS

Packer, Jenkins, Ansible, Terraform, Azure

- The goal of this project was to migrate an application which was hosted on-prem to Microsoft Azure.
- Since the application was a monolith, The decision was made to use Packer create an Image via a Jenkins Pipeline which was then stored in the Azure Shared Image Gallery.
- Once the image was created, Terraform was used to deploy the image as a VM onto Azure. The application also had an external Azure Postgres Server for storing the created Databases.
- Post VM deployment, The configuration of the machine was handled by Ansible roles which were fed into a Linux Daemon to be run whenever the VM restarted or on its first boot. In a nut shell, the configuration of the VM included calls to the API's handling the product and also performed certificate exchange to establish trust with the clients.

Terraform Cloud Workspace Creation - Automation

Terraform Cloud, Shell Scripting, Jenkins

- The goal of this project was to create Terraform Cloud Workspaces without any manual intervention.
- Here, I wrote a bash script which established an API Driven workflow for Terraform Cloud, thereby creating workspaces and populating them with workspace-specific variables.

Azure Kubernetes Cluster Creation and Upgrades - Automation

Terraform Cloud, Azure AKS, Shell Scripting, Jenkins, Terratest

- The goal of this project was to automate the process of creating and upgrading Azure Kubernetes Clusters.
- Terraform Scripts were written by using native terraform resources provided on their official website. A wrapper shell script was added to call the Terraform scripts via Jenkins. Finally, Testing of the entire approach was performed via Terratest.

Migrating from a Relational Database to AWS DynamoDB

AWS DMS, AWS EC2, AWS DynamoDB

- The goal of this project was to migrate a normalized relational database to an Amazon DynamoDB table in order to optimize on cost savings.
- The various tasks involved were investigating the source database(relational), designing the data model and creating the DynamoDB table, creating the DMS task mapping rules and finally testing the access patterns.

AWS Site-to-Site VPN

AWS EC2, AWS VPC

- Created an AWS Site-to-Site VPN connection using 2 AWS VPC's in different regions altogether.
- The process of creating the VPN connection was carried out by installing and configuring a software-based customer VPN gateway running on an EC2 instance. Openswan was used as the VPN solution as it provides a complete IPsec implementation.

Monitoring Kubernetes Applications using Prometheus and Grafana

Kubernetes, Prometheus, Grafana

- Installed and configured prometheus and grafana in a kubernetes cluster.
- Setup basic grafana dashboards to chalk out application specific as well as cluster specific performance details.
- Prometheus was used to collect raw data from the cluster whereas Grafana was used to display graphs, heatmaps etc.

CERTIFICATIONS

- AWS Certified Solutions Architect Professional
- Google Cloud Certified Professional Cloud Architect
- HashiCorp Certified Vault Operations Professional
- HashiCorp Certified Consul Associate
- HashiCorp Certified Vault Associate
- HashiCorp Certified Terraform Associate
- CNCF Certified Kubernetes Security Specialist
- Microsoft Certified Azure Administrator Associate
- AWS Certified Solutions Architect Associate
- CNCF Certified Kubernetes Administrator
- HackerRank-REST API(Intermediate Level)
- Coursera-Specialization Certification- Cloud Architecture with Google Cloud
- Scored 170/190 in Cambridge Business English Certificate Vantage Level
- Database Management Systems and Cloud Computing certified by NPTEL

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Languages: Go, Python, Bash, HCL
- Cloud Services: Amazon Web Services, Azure, Google Cloud Platform
- Version Control: Git
- Container Technologies: Kubernetes, Docker, Service Meshes(Consul, Istio)
- Monitoring Tools: Prometheus, Grafana
- DevOps: Linux, Jenkins, Ansible, Chef, Packer
- HashiCorp Suite: Vault, Boundary, Terraform and Consul
- Others: Public Key Infrastructure, OpenID Connect

EDUCATION

Vardhaman College Of Engineering

Bachelor of Technology in Information Technology; CGPA: 9.13

Hyderabad, India

Aug. 2016 - Sept. 2020